<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?><rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:openSearch="http://a9.com/-/spec/opensearchrss/1.0/" xmlns:blogger="http://schemas.google.com/blogger/2008" xmlns:georss="http://www.georss.org/georss" xmlns:gd="http://schemas.google.com/g/2005" xmlns:thr="http://purl.org/syndication/thread/1.0" version="2.0"><channel><atom:id>tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8053363912668035563</atom:id><lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2015 18:56:27 +0000</lastBuildDate><title>Loyola Bioethics</title><description>A commitment to educating health care professionals to be effective leaders for social justice in medicine and society.</description><link>http://loyolabioethics.blogspot.com/</link><managingEditor>noreply@blogger.com (Loyola Bioethics)</managingEditor><generator>Blogger</generator><openSearch:totalResults>12</openSearch:totalResults><openSearch:startIndex>1</openSearch:startIndex><openSearch:itemsPerPage>25</openSearch:itemsPerPage><item><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:blogger.com,1999:blog-8053363912668035563.post-6524566442595490668</guid><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2015 14:52:00 +0000</pubDate><atom:updated>2015-05-18T09:03:47.712-05:00</atom:updated><title>The Dreamer Committee* of Loyola University Chicago: Promoting Dignity through Education</title><description>&lt;b&gt;Loyola University Chicago&lt;/b&gt; has been a leader in working for educational opportunity for Undocumented students, i.e., persons who were brought to the United States as children and were raised and educated in this country, but remain without a path to normalization of their immigration status.&amp;nbsp; They are often said to be "Americans in every way but on paper."&amp;nbsp; Many of these Undocumented students have been granted temporary relief through the executive action of President Obama on June 15, 2012. The President created the Deferred Action for Childhood Arrivals (DACA) program that grants two-year renewable stays of action and also provides an Employment Authorization Document (i.e., a "work permit") and enables them to apply for a social security number. However, it provides no path to permanent residency or citizenship and does not enable them to access any federal programs such as student loans. As a result, these students have a minimally-legal status that limits their educational opportunity.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;table cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;tr-caption-container&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 1em; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-t3bx4FOIBEE/VTe04fQt_QI/AAAAAAAAAGQ/7s489ahLI-s/s1600/kaufka-walts.JPG&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;clear: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-t3bx4FOIBEE/VTe04fQt_QI/AAAAAAAAAGQ/7s489ahLI-s/s1600/kaufka-walts.JPG&quot; width=&quot;183&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;tr-caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Katherine Kaufka Walts&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;The &lt;b&gt;Dreamer Committee&lt;/b&gt; is a university-wide standing committee that succeeds a major task force that reviewed Loyola's progress in meeting the needs of these students (For a recap of the work of the task force, see the presentations by &lt;i&gt;Katherine Kaufka Walts, Kathleen Maas Weigert, Mark Kuczewski&lt;/i&gt;, and &lt;i&gt;Flavio Bravo &lt;/i&gt;given at the Forum on Teaching and Learning (FOTL). The task force found that Loyola University Chicago had become an emerging national leader in promoting equity for these students. Achievements included the Stritch School of Medicine becoming the first U.S. medical school to openly welcome DACA-eligible students (&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.stritch.luc.edu/daca&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;www.stritch.luc.edu/daca&lt;/a&gt;) and the incredible undergraduate effort that create the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.ibtimes.com/immigration-reform-2015-loyola-university-votes-increase-fees-support-undocumented-1882924&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Magis Scholarship Fund for Undocumented students&lt;/a&gt; from a self-imposed student activity fee.&amp;nbsp; Such "firsts" have brought the university renown and highlighted the value all levels of the university place on social justice. However, progress was uneven across the schools of the university and sustained attention needed to be given to these issues.&amp;nbsp; The collaboration of dedicated faculty, administrators, and students is needed to further opportunity for Undocumented students at Loyola and to seek systemic change in our nation's immigration system through scholarship and advocacy.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;Mission&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The mission of the Dreamer Committee is to develop equitable policies and practices to promote educational opportunities and improve the lives of undocumented students at Loyola University Chicago. This will be achieved by through multidisciplinary collaboration, and the promotion of research, education, advocacy and service that is informed by the lives and experiences of undocumented students seeking higher education. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;div style=&quot;text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;table cellpadding=&quot;0&quot; cellspacing=&quot;0&quot; class=&quot;tr-caption-container&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 1em; text-align: left;&quot;&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-gw5ZOCxY3uM/UzNCA_-LF3I/AAAAAAAAABw/5aAIwuB4b8k/s1600/Kuczewski-2.jpg&quot; imageanchor=&quot;1&quot; style=&quot;clear: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;&quot;&gt;&lt;img border=&quot;0&quot; height=&quot;200&quot; src=&quot;http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-gw5ZOCxY3uM/UzNCA_-LF3I/AAAAAAAAABw/5aAIwuB4b8k/s1600/Kuczewski-2.jpg&quot; width=&quot;150&quot; /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class=&quot;tr-caption&quot; style=&quot;text-align: center;&quot;&gt;Mark Kuczewski&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;The mission of the Dreamer Committee is grounded in the Catholic and Jesuit mission to promote social justice and in the bedrock principle that acceptance of undocumented students is part of Loyola University Chicago's broader culture of acceptance, inclusion, safety and support. As a Catholic university that is sponsored by the Society of Jesus (the Jesuits), we firmly believe in the dignity of each person and in the promotion of social justice. The dignity of persons calls us to steward the talents of qualified applicants rather than reject their contributions for arbitrary and arcane reasons, including immigration status. Social justice requires that we foster the conditions for full participation in the community by all members of our community. Undocumented, DACA, and DACA eligible applicants are typically woven into the fabric of our communities and have a basic right to contribute to the fullest extent of their abilities. This approach echoes a long tradition articulated by the U.S. Conference of Catholic Bishops (USCCB) of advocacy for immigrant members of our communities. &lt;i&gt;[Excerpt from the UCUS report]&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;What the Dreamer Committee will do: Policy, Scholarship, Education&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;As indicated in our mission statement, the admission and financial aid policies and practices of each school will be studied. Progress and successes will be noted and best practices shared across schools. Strategies for fundraising and funding students will be priorities for action. As noted, there is an urgency to the issue of funding for these students as they lack eligibility for federal student aid, a key element in the financial aid packages of many students. &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;The main work of a university is scholarly and educational. Thus the Committee will develop a network of support for the many faculty currently creating relevant scholarship.&amp;nbsp; The Committee will foster collaboration among these scholars and promote their work.&amp;nbsp; And, creative educational approaches and programming will be shared and new educational efforts will follow from this cross fertilization. This kind of inquiry and teaching that is in the service of the University's Jesuit ideals of social justice and human dignity is central to the university's self-understanding and strategic vision.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Loyola University Chicago believes in education that is transformative of the person.&amp;nbsp; Those who participate in a Jesuit education are intellectually and personally formed such that they are aware of persons who are unjustly marginalized and this understanding results in action. The Dreamer Committee seeks to model this Ignatian dynamic within our university community and to promote justice for our immigrant neighbors within and beyond the walls of our campus.&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;Co-Chairs:&lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.luc.edu/chrc/katherine_bio.shtml&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Katherine Kaufka Walts, JD&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;Director, Center for Human Rights of Children&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;br /&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hsd1.luc.edu/bioethics/aboutus/facultydirectory/people/markkuczewskiphd/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mark Kuczewski, PhD&lt;/a&gt; &lt;br /&gt;The Fr. Michael I. English Professor of Medical Ethics, Stritch School of Medicine&lt;br /&gt;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp;&amp;nbsp; &lt;br /&gt;The following presentations (YouTube video) from the Loyola &lt;i&gt;Forum on Teaching and Learning&lt;/i&gt; summarize the work of the University Collaborative on Undocumented Students (UCUS).&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;b&gt;&quot;DREAMers Welcome: Living the Loyola Mission through Educating Undocumented Students&quot;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/ghPCu6EP3nc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Katherine Kaufka Walts&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/BRxi3yebZW8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mark Kuczewski&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://youtu.be/EPIIvslf2ug&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kathleen Maas-Weigert&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://youtu.be/DzC1Wwa5ZPg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Flavio Bravo&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;*The name of this working group, &lt;i&gt;Dreamer Committee&lt;/i&gt;, is to convey the commitment to Undocumented students at Loyola who inspire, strive for more, and achieve excellence.&amp;nbsp; &lt;ul&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;</description><link>http://loyolabioethics.blogspot.com/2015/04/the-dreamer-committee-of-loyola.html</link><author>noreply@blogger.com (Loyola Bioethics)</author><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-t3bx4FOIBEE/VTe04fQt_QI/AAAAAAAAAGQ/7s489ahLI-s/s72-c/kaufka-walts.JPG" height="72" width="72"/><thr:total>0</thr:total></item></channel></rss>